Finding aid to the John Tappan Stoddard Papers CA.MS.00321
Smith College Archives
John Tappan Stoddard Papers
1877-2001
Smith College Archives
Stoddard, John Tappan, 1852-1919
CA.MS.00321
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Professor of physics 1878-1880, professor of chemistry 1880-1919. Contains biographical material, correspondence, photographs, and publications.
Biographical / Historical
John Tappan Stoddard was born October 20, 1852 to William H. and Helen H. Stoddard in Northampton, Massachusetts. He is a descendant of Solomon Stoddard, the second minister of Northampton, known for the "halfway covenant" and for being the grandfather of Jonathan Edwards. On June 26, John Stoddard married Mary Grover Leavitt, with whom he would have two sons and a daughter.
Stoddard graduated from Amherst College in 1874. He served as Assistant Principle of Northampton High in 1875 before going to the University of Göttingen, where he studied under Hans Hubner and received his doctorate in 1878.
In 1878 Stoddard was appointed by President Seeyle as the instructor of Mathematics and Physics. In 1881 he became head of the departments of physics and chemistry and in 1897 became the head of the chemistry department. He was the "heart and soul" of Colloquium, a departmental chemistry club where informal discussions about the subject could be conducted between students and faculty similar to seminars in the German universities.
Stoddard is also credited with inventing the Stoddard test tube clamp around 1886, a device which is still used today.
John Tappan Stoddard served Smith College for 41 years. Following Stoddard's sudden death on December 9, 1919, the Chemistry building of the college, which he helped design, was named in his honor.
Scope and Contents
Contains biographical material, correspondence, photographs, and publications.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The John Tappan Stoddard papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Stoddard, John Tappan, 1852-1919
- Biographical Information, 1887-2001 (Box 1026, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1883-1952 (Box 1026, Folder 2)
- Photographs, 1880-1904 (Box 1026, Folder 3)
- Photographs - Stoddard Homestead, 1891 (Box 1026, Folder 4)
- Publications, 1877-1909 (Box 1026, Folder 5)
- Introduction to General Chemistry, 1910 (Box 1026, Folder 6)
- Introduction to Organic Chemistry, 1918 (Box 1026, Folder 7)
- Outline of Lecture Notes on General Chemistry, 1889 (Box 1026, Folder 8)
- Outline of Qualitative Analysis for Beginners, 1883 (Box 1026, Folder 9)
- The Science of Billiards, 1913 (Box 1026, Folder 10)